another videos the two most important
people in your network in your
professional Learning Network Your
Personal Learning Network whatever you
call it your pln are your mentor and
your recruiter and we'll talk we
separate videos about that but the we're
going to talk about what it means uh to
have a mentor and what the relationship
is
about understanding this is
understanding the role of uh a mentor
okay and it's really important that you
get this okay because if you don't get
it as a person who needs help you can
end up losing your mentor and if you uh
are a mentor you might end up overc
committing and getting burned out and
not actually helping the person at all
so understanding that relationship is
super important and I am going to make
very objective scientific references to
the most successful mentorship uh
program I have ever participated in the
Boy Scouts of America now I before you
turn to video off and go away and and
start writing horrible things about
pedophiles and stuff like that in the
Boy Scout program I'm not talking about
that okay so let's just like put all of
that aside and let's let's just observe
the most successful volunteer mentorship
program that has ever existed in the
United States in my opinion so let's
talk about we're going to talk this is
kind of story-wise we're going to go
into this we're going to describe why
that program is so successful and how it
worked and where it came to be what
problem was it solving and all of those
you know points are going to relate to
how you can find a good Mentor and how
that Mentor can uh use their time best
and how you can be respectful of the
time etc etc etc um yeah but let's not
let's not go there I shouldn't have even
gone there myself let's just stick with
the the whole thing so the boys CS of
America I just pull disclosure I was you
know a Mormon and I was a I was a boy
scat I never made it to Eagle but I
could have I was uh regular
um a scout master for many many years um
I raised four Sons um so I've been in
the program a lot and there's something
called uh a merit badge counselor and I
have to describe this in order for you
to get it so just just hang with me for
a bit here what a merit badge counselor
is is there somebody who has been vetted
by the boy guests of America they have
applied they filled out paperwork uh to
be a volunteer and so they don't
officially they're not officially part
of you know the the core leadership of a
scout troop or that kind of thing they
are volunteers they're volunteers on the
side and they they spend a large amount
of their time uh preparing material and
answering questions and being the mentor
uh for a scout whose job it is to
identify them find them and do most of
the work on their own and then go to
their merit badge counsil or their
mentor and validate the work that they
have done sound familiar okay so that
Dynamic which was invented and I don't
even remember his name um you know it
was a pseudo military kind of situation
but that it was invented because they
understood that the people who had the
experience uh were not going to and that
had the relevant experience were not
going to have a lot of time and I did
another who should you learn from video
and I touched on this topic a little bit
as well uh but I want to get more deep
into that dynamic because it's super
important we're going to ask the
questions about is this appropriate to
do this or this or this you know
regarding the time constraint um so so
again this video is for you if you want
to be a mentor or you want to be
mentored how does that Dynamic even work
um the first step is you need you know
you need the the the the responsibility
for the learning and there's other stuff
on this is the is you the person doing
the learning that is the person who's
responsible to do the learning and
decide what it is they want to learn how
they want to learn it who their mentors
are they're the ones who have to seek
Scout these people now The Scouting
program made it nice and easy because
they would have a list of approved uh
you know checked off and vetted U
mentors um May batch counselors for any
particular topic and then they could go
to the list and if somebody was working
on a thing they had you know they would
actually sign off on a little card
saying okay I hav't you know entered
into a mentorship relationship with this
MBS counselor it was all tracked and
then the merit badge counselor could
keep kind of track of what they had done
as well and they also had a very you
know well delineated a list of tasks and
projects that and requirements which is
something I've always wanted to be able
to do for tech at one point actually I
was playing around with the idea of tech
Scouts you know because um you know
there's so many things uh that cross
over um you know it's it's really task
based like how to do a thing or whatever
and and so anyway so you've got this
relationship established and then after
that the the regular things so let's say
you're meeting with your Mentor once a
week um or less uh you're expected to
come to the session ready and if you
ever show up to one of these volunteer
Mentor mer padge people's house uh or
wherever it is that you meet I think
sometimes you have to meet in a public
area obviously um but if you do and
you're not ready and you're just like
hey okay tell me what to do teacher no
no the the the the expectation and the
dynamic is you are doing the work you're
doing the research and you're getting
stuck you're getting blocked you're
getting questions you can't figure out
you're getting like what is what is
really they're really talking about here
you are doing the hard work and you're
like jotting it down you're writing it
down and you're putting you're you're
delineating those things that you need
to bring up with your mentor and then
and then that hour that precious
precious hour I mean most of the people
that are going to be mentoring you in
Tech or anything like that their time is
going to be worth at least 80 bucks an
hour so you're probably not going to be
paying them 80 bucks an hour and they're
going to be doing it out of the goodness
of their heart and by the way if if do
not do not assume anybody is going to do
it for free because they know you
they're in a family or something like
that don't do that the first thing you
should do as a as a person to be Mentor
is when you approach them I don't care
if they're your brother or your sister
or somebody you still need to respect
their time and you should offer them if
you have money of any kind you should
offer them something in exchange for
their time and I don't it's up to you to
decide what that is but I but but
walking into relationship because you
know your uncle is in Tech and you're
like oh he loves me and yeah he's going
to do it all for free and I'm just going
to go hey can you spend two hours with
me teaching me how to code don't do that
because you're going to put that person
that volunteer on the spot now this is
one place where it differs from The
Scouting program because the scouting
program has already a bunch of people
who have volunteered a certain amount of
their time per week or per month or
whatever and they've committed it to the
program they've already openly said that
and what this one of this is one of the
things is so great about the scouts is
that it's it's it's already got all the
framework for facilitating learning
because you can you can go out you can
go reach out to these people who have
already volunteered their time and you
they don't you don't have to find them
now you getting into Tech unfortunately
you need to find these people and one of
the reasons that we do the beginner
boost this way and that we have this big
Learning Community where we all come
together and we're all in here together
veterans and you know people that are
learning of all types is to facilitate
that now the problem is I can't vet
anybody I can't say that so and so over
here is a good person to talk to to
about this or this and such and some and
so over here as a better person and you
know it's up to you to to do that
assessment of the mentor and that
probably needs to be uh a separate video
I did a video already on that called who
do you want to learn from and I really
feel like that covers it but to just
recap that it means that you want people
with experience you want people with
current experience that means your best
mentors are going to be people that are
doing the job most of the time they're
going to be employed and most of the
time they're not going to be even paid
for what for for mentoring are going to
be paid professionally they they haven't
made a career out of mentoring people
they made a career out of doing the
thing that you want to learn those are
always better people to learn from I
that I mean that goes it should go
without saying but you have to say it
anyway there's a video about that so so
the Mente goes to you know they identify
the mentor and the mentor's got to
decide okay now what do I do with this
kid or this
person by Kid I usually mean like it
could be somebody who's 40 years old I
mean I'm 56 so to me there are still a
kid so so if somebody somebody pops in
and yeah buy him a meal that's a great
idea Mark um you know and sometimes this
by the way you can be the same age it
could be somebody who who's in cyber
security and you have no idea how to do
that it could be somebody who just got
their data certificate or their data
science certificate and they want to
help you get get into data science wink
wink Mark um you know there's a lot of
people out there that could be your
professional mentors uh buy them a copy
that's another great idea um but so from
the Mente side number one don't just
jump in expecting somebody to do it for
free you should respect their time
number one number two look for people
and this is a video on this look for
people who have experience and time and
are willing to dedicate and and and
number three figure out a way to
approach them uh and and and find them
and how do you find these people um you
know I think that probably should be its
own video but that's just building your
own pln there's lots of other videos
about how to build a pln and I'm not
going to break that down but you know
meetups All That Jazz you know
communities like this one blah blah blah
um okay so then let's talk about it
let's talk about this M mentee
relationship um compared to the to the
scouting organization from the mentor uh
position um I just about oh hey hi I'm
making a video how are you God you're
cute my my wife she's got her cute
little shorts on she left the dog out
the dog is finally okay the dog was
sitting underneath underneath my feet
because we had a thunderstorm
outside um yeah we'll talk about
LinkedIn later um so so let's talk about
the mentor relationship and I almost
pivoted all the skill sack when I
started it about Midway through so
something like
20176 and turned it into an organization
kind of like how bridges out of poverty
trains people to deal with homelessness
and help you know rid the the world of
homelessness I was like I wanted to
spend time you know mentoring mentors
helping them to you know to do it and so
I'm talking to them right now so if you
want to be a mar badge counselor a tech
Mar badge counselor or a mentor of any
kind you probably have a lot of
questions about how to do that and what
does it even look like and and what's
appropriate and all that stuff and I
honestly I really want to make a a
separate series off of the Boost that's
just for people who want to Mentor the
world needs you the world needs more
mentors more good qualified employed
mentors who can can give up an hour or
two of their day and they can take on
one or two people that they Mentor uh in
what it is that they do the blacksmith
analogy uh the the padwan analogy and
that you know it is May the four today
so um so what how do how do you do that
the first answer is what what happens
during the time when you meet the answer
I already touched on this but I'm going
touch it again the mentor's job is to
answer questions and help the person get
unstuck and and help them see
alternative paths through their thing so
let's take some specific examples uh I
once had a kid I once had a kid come in
he was new he was come in and he sat
down and he leaned back in his
chair I mean he was all you know chill
and everything and I and I just sat
down I drank my
coffee hey how's it going oh great he's
like this he
like so what are we doing today teacher
what we got to do what are we going to
do I said I don't know what are we going
to do and he was
like
what you tell me what are we gonna
do it blew his mind it blew his mind his
whole mind was because he was like
you're in charge I like this is your
time this is your time you tell me what
we need to
do and he was like well you're the
teacher you're supposed to he even said
it you're the teacher you're supposed to
tell me what to do I and this is why I
hate the term
teacher this is I hate the term teacher
and play video we did that actually many
times we play you know what's funny
there were sometimes there was this is a
great thing about a mentor relationship
um I actually played a lot of OverWatch
and Minecraft with the people that I
Mentor so many of them didn't have an
opportunity to just to just relax
sometimes so at the end the last 20
minutes or so I would sometimes use
Minecraft or OverWatch or whatever as as
an as a as a we used to call it code in
play and we would actually play some
video games at the end and they knew it
was coming so they would it kind of
worked against us sometimes because they
would they didn't care about the
learning they just want to get to the
game part but yeah we would actually
play games together and sometimes it was
fun and and you know they were paying me
and and their parents knew it and
sometimes you know that connection was
fun so I'm not saying don't play games
but but the idea was that it was in
their hands and I so the other the other
side of this is I there was a guy the
guy I talk about him all the time but
there was a guy who actually no I won't
talk about him I'll talk about my group
I had a group called Pro and this group
was these are people that had been with
me for a long time they were very very
autodidactic they took control they
always had projects they were working on
and they would practically cut each
other's throat to get my attention when
they were all at Pro together we'd have
a pro segment for 90 minutes we'd all
get together in the room and and I would
sit down with each one of them I Tred to
rotate around but they would almost like
elbow each other out of the way because
they wanted to show me what they were
working on and they had questions to ask
me and they they they were ready there
they just they had they knew in fact my
they knew that my time was was precious
so they would deliberately prepare
themselves so when they got time with me
like okay well I got this one thing
right
here and it was like a lab it was like a
learning lab and I have a saying learn
you know learning happens in the lab not
the lecture hall and that's what it was
it was a lab now the downside of that
was and the reason I eventually went to
one of my mentoring is because it became
there started to be drama between the
people I used to you know it's like you
know you know Mr Rob doesn't spend as
much time with me as he spends with so
and so and it was it got really ugly but
it was the opposite problem it was the
opposite problem it wasn't what we doing
today teacher it was like I I have five
more minutes I have five more minutes
can you help me answer this question
here it was the opposite problem these
people were so prepared for time with
their Mentor that that I did I didn't
have enough time to to spend with them
because it because it was you know but
they knew they knew right away what the
expectation was the other one had to
learn that when they came if they didn't
do anything all
week then I I would say okay look did
you have any time to do anything this
week and about 50% of the people I
mentored and I hate saying this about
50% of the people that I mentored said
that they didn't have any time to work
on anything for the the entire week and
I'm like really you really didn't work
on anything this week you didn't have
any time to work on anything this week I
was like okay well let's work on
something for this hour and we would sit
down together and we would type out
stuff and work on at that hour and by
the way that's how we've been doing the
beginner boost for the last three years
we're not doing it that way this year I
will do some of those things and I will
record a video so you can work along
with me but I am not going to hold your
hand no and I don't think you should
have your hand held and if you're going
to be a mentor you need to push back on
the people that you're helping and say
no you are in control control of your
learning here if you don't know what you
should do let's brainstorm some projects
for you together and that is something
that comes up all the time during this
beginner boo session people don't know
what to do they don't know oh what
should I do and that's a separate video
but the the responsibility for doing the
learning and finding the project rests
on the person doing the learning and as
a mentor you need to push back to them
the first time that you start saying
this is this is what you're going to do
you're going to do X and Y and Z so help
me God and you start cracking the whip
you are are no longer a facilitator
you're no longer a mentor and frankly
you're no longer effective because the
person who's doing the learning now
feels like you're doing the directing
for them it's like the dad who builds
the whole Pinewood Derby car instead of
the
kid and there's at least one person who
got that
reference so hopefully this is this has
been a way to talk about the Dynamics
between the mentor and the mentee the
lessons learned from the very successful
scouting program for the mer patch
specifically the merit badge program and
yes I have thought about doing Tech
merit badges I have I have thought about
doing that I've thought about organizing
all the tech stuff in that way I may
still come up with something like that
but until but we don't have to do that
right now you just need to know about
the dynamic and the dynamic between the
mentor and the Mente depending on which
one you want to be if you have questions
about how to be a mentor or how to
approach people to get to be a mentor
there's a Discord there's our regular
you know Saturday time for the beginner
boost which is right now um and you know
I I cannot always add address every
question you have but we are here for
you and we want to see mentorship and
and continue to improve um and and get
big so